now the question is we have this type of devices
and they are connected us we just saw the
question is how can the processor give commands
and data to the specific controller when it wants
to do I/O?
so there are basically two ways to go the first way
to go here is to have basically direct communication
with the controllers so the CPU in this case
is reading and writing directly into the registers
the small memories of the controllers with
special instructions that allow the CPU to directly
communicate with the devices
so if the CPU wants to issue a request
to read something from the disk then it will
go and read and write registers that belong
to the controller that is the one behind which
you have the disks
the alternative way is to use and this is
what is commonly used memory mapped I/O
in this case the registers of the controllers
are mapped into the main memory so in the address
space of the processor that are special parts of the main
memory that are actually mirrors
if you want of the registers of the different
devices now then the CPU writes and reads only
main memory but when it writes or reads to specific
portions of it what is doing is actually writing
and reading to the registers of specific controllers
you can also use at the same time both ways
of communication depending on the devices
you want to communicate with so this is version
one here the CPU has dedicated channels physically
wires that are used the allow the CPU to run dedicated
instructions that can write or read specific bytes
in the memory of the controller
so in this case the CPU needs to have special
instructions what it wants for example to
read or write from the disk or read and write from the
network card and so on the alternative is to rely on someone
sitting in the middle between the CPU and
the different controllers
and this will be usually the motherboard to
memory-mapped I/O so in this case parts as I said
of the main memory are mirrors of the registers
of the devices and it's the motherboard that
takes care of keeping these copies consistent
so that whenever the CPU writes or reads into memory
actually these the information that is
being written
into the registers is moved also to the controller
when the controller updates this information
that information is also brought back to that main memory
for the CPU to see that the information has changed
an example a classic example is
the graphics controller
there is a significantly large part of the
memory that is used to hold the screen contents
this is memory-mapped I/O the processor
sends the output for the screen what you are
going to see on the screen right in this special
region of the memory
and then the motherboard takes care of sharing
this data with the graphics controller that translates
that into the thing that you actually see
on screen and this is just an example of the
specific portions of memory which are reserved
for a specific controller for example for
this controller and so on for the graphics controller and so on
now the registers you have usually are the following
ones for the controllers you have to data in register
this is read by the host to get input and
the data out register which is written by
the host to send output the host here would be the CPU
and then you have the status registers that contain bits
that can be read by the host these are bits indicating
for example whether the current command has completed
whether a byte is available to be read or whether or a device
error has occurred and so it depends of course on the type
of controller you are communicating with
you have control registers to start commands or to
change the mode of a device so let's see
for example you can have a certain bit in
the control register of a set of serial port to chose
between full duplex or only haf-duplex for the communication
so one direction on both directions at the
same time or you can have bits that are set
by the host to specify the word length let's say to seven or
eight bits that are supported by a specific
serial port